<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of Sir Audley Mervyn, knight, His Majesties prime Serjeant at Law, and speaker of the House of Commons in Ireland delivered to His Grace James Duke of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, the 13 day of February, 1662, in the Presence-chamber in the castle of Dublin : containing the sum of affairs in Ireland, but more especially, the interest of adventurers and souldiers.</title>
            <author>Mervyn, Audley, Sir, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R904</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12770220</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12770220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of Sir Audley Mervyn, knight, His Majesties prime Serjeant at Law, and speaker of the House of Commons in Ireland delivered to His Grace James Duke of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, the 13 day of February, 1662, in the Presence-chamber in the castle of Dublin : containing the sum of affairs in Ireland, but more especially, the interest of adventurers and souldiers.</title>
                  <author>Mervyn, Audley, Sir, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Dublin and re-printed at London by J. Streater,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPEECH OF Sir <hi>Audley Mervyn</hi> Knight; His Majeſties Prime Serjeant at Law, And Speaker of the Houſe of Commons in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Delivered to His Grace <hi>JAMES</hi> Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi>Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi>the <hi>13</hi> day of <hi>February, 1662.</hi> in the Preſence-Chamber in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing the Sum of Affairs in <hi>Ireland;</hi> But more eſpecially, the Intereſt of ADVENTURERS and SOULDIERS.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>DUBLIN;</hi> And Reprinted at <hi>LONDON</hi> by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> by Speciall Order, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93645:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93645:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The SPEECH of Sir</hi> AUDLEY MERVYN Knight, <hi>His Majeſties Prime Serjeant at Law, and Speaker of the Houſe of COMMONS in</hi> Ireland: <hi>Delivered to</hi> JAMES <hi>Duke of</hi> ORMOND, <hi>Lord Lieutenant of</hi> Ireland, <hi>the</hi> 13 <hi>day of</hi> February, 1662. <hi>in the Preſence Chamber in the Caſtle of</hi> Dublin.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the ancient Priviledges of our Houſe, We have been humble Suitors for this Acceſs into the Royal Preſence: and your private Spirit which knows not how to deny, prevails ſo in your publick Capacity, that even for this your Graces particular condiſcention, I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes in Parliament aſſembled, to preſent you their moſt Submiſſive acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And ſurely this preſent Solemnity of the Houſe attending your Grace, may carry the ſignification of a Hand in the Margent, to point out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then of ordinary obſervation.</p>
            <p>This, with us, is as a ſheet-Anchor, which is never made ready but when we diſcern a cloud; perchance it is yet no bigger than a mans Hand, but by the beſt Judgment we can make of it, it is like to over-caſt the Horizon of this Kingdom; This makes this Addreſs of that Importance, that the Houſe thought not fit to entruſt it to the bare expreſſions of a Speaker, (had he been of the greateſt abilities,) therefore have they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it to this Inſtrument, that it might remain as a Record of their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, that the hard Fate and Ruine of an Engliſh Intereſt in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might not bear date under the beſt of Kings, under ſo vigilant a Lord Lieutenant, under the firſt (and if not prevented, like to be the laſt) Proteſtant Parliament that ever ſate in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>It would confound Aſtrologers to obſerve ſuch Planets, ſuch maſculine Planets, aſcending, in Conjunction, in the Houſes of their Exaltation, and yet this Kingdom not to be Planet-ſtruck.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93645:3"/>
            <p>There is a time to ſpeak, and a time to hold our peace; This, this, is the Critical time, God calls us to it, when Religion, the eſtabliſht Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is in danger to be undermined, by caſting the predominancy of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per upon a Popiſh Intereſt: And believe it Sir, whatſoever deluſive Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents have been broached a late, the contrary hath been written in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of bloud, not in his Majeſties Kingdoms onely, but whereſoever the Papal power was exalted; That perſons profeſſing the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are but Tenants at Will for their Lives and For unes, and through Centuries of Ages it appears, That as their Fleeces grow they are ſhorn, till a time of ſlaughter be appointed.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty, He hath called us by his Writ to no other end, but to offer up our humble Advice, <hi>Nè quid detrimenti reſpublica capiat;</hi> And if ever the advice of Subjects may be ſerviceable to their Prince, this is the time, when this poor, miſerable, and unfortunate Kingdom, fruitful by the bloud of Engliſh, and plac't as a greedy grave to bury their treaſure in from age to age, is upon its new module: It is now in its Mintage, and our care muſt be, that the Miter be not ſtampt inſtead of the Crown; It is not long ſince the ſale of this Kingdom was offered to the Miter, as his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Intereſt was proſtituted to every Roman Catholick power, ſo that it may be ſaid of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as <hi>Jugurtha</hi> ſaid of <hi>Rome, O venalem Hiberniam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ox perituram ſi modò emptorem invenerit:</hi> Did I ſay his Majeſty call'd Us? May his Majeſties days be long, and proſperous; Were we weltring in our bloud, We muſt hold water whileſt he waſhes his Hands in Innocency.</p>
            <p>The Country calls Us, and were they not aſſured We would ſpeak for them, doubtleſs but your Grace had heard them ſpeak for themſelves by their humble Petitions, for the Alarum, that <hi>Hannibal</hi> is at the Gates, is hot throughout the Proteſtant Plantations; We are his Majeſties Great Council, the grand Inqueſt of the Kingdom, and We dare appeal to your Grace, how We have ſpent our time: We underſtand the uſual proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Parliaments, to begin at Grievances, and conclude with Supplies; We have inverted the Order, and applyed our ſelves hitherto in ſettling a conſtant Revenue for his Majeſty, and granting other Temporary ayds far above our abilities, yet far leſs then what his Majeſties goodneſs may challenge from us: There hath been an imitable contention, as I may ſay, between the King and his Parliament here, if it were poſſible for a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to out-do ſuch a King, We would; but 'tis poſſible for a King, and he hath out-done us, and therefore <hi>væh illis,</hi> Wo be to them, that in this Conjunction would undo us both.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93645:3"/>
            <p>It muſt be therefore a forc't Put, that preſſeth us on to this addreſs and our moderation even in it will appear; <hi>Cuncta prius tentanda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in the body Politique as it is in the natural; he brawny and fleſhy members can admit a diſcontinuity of parts, though not without pain, yet without danger; But the apple of the eye is ſo tender, that the leaſt duſt is offenſive to it: We enjoy the benefit of many good and wholſom Laws, But the Act of Settlement is the Law of Laws, it is the <hi>Magra Charta Hiberniæ,</hi> this is the apple of the eye, and muſt be Printed with this Motto: <hi>Nemo me impune laceſſit:</hi> Our ſtrength lies in this, as <hi>Sampſons</hi> in his locks; if thoſe be cut, we are as weak as others, when the Philiſtins, ſhall fall upon us, in the execution of other Laws, whether <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> in this we fulfill the weightyer things of the Law.</p>
            <p>Your Grace well remembers that ſtrugling twins in the Womb of this Act, never Prince that ſat upon the Throne, endured ſo many pongs and throws, to give his Proteſtant Subjects a Birth and Life, as CHARLES the Second did: And We ſhall never forget the fainting expectations of the People for this Bill of Settlement, when every ones Soul look't out at the Caſements of his eyes, as <hi>Sicera's</hi> mother, with a <hi>Why are the wheels of his Charirt ſo long a coming?</hi> But now Sir, with as great a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row We behold the driving of the Chariot to belike the driving of <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Son of <hi>Nemiſh</hi> that drove furiouſly.</p>
            <p>We come not this day to reflect upon the Commiſſionrs for executing the ſaid Act: This Houſe hath a great reſpect for that Court, it had part of our, breath to give it life, and we are under the greateſt obligations to admire his Majeſties goodneſs and favour to his Proteſtants, (I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verforget the expreſſion of his Majeſty at a full Council,) my Juſtice I muſt afford to you all, but my favour muſt be plac't upon my Proteſtant Subjects, in ſending over thoſe Gentlemen, that were of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and Religion: His Majeſty warrantably judged, that if difference were betwixt an Iſraelite and Egyptian, <hi>Moſes,</hi> would lean to the Iſr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elite: His Majeſty knew men of reſolition might alter the Climate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out changing ſound Principles, though even thoſe may be indanger'd by a conſtant and familiar converſation, with perſons of different judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and ſo we may in time forget to atteſt the fear of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and learn to ſwear by the life of <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> We conſider the comprehenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Act, their new beaten path of proceedings, <hi>ſæpe viatoremnova: nonvetus orbita fallit;</hi> The mixture in Hotch pot of Law and equity,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93645:4"/>ſo that they are both Jurors and Judges, and the rſummaineſs of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings they deſigne, ſo that the Text many times may happen not to be the Rule, but the Hower-Glaſs; His Majeſties other Courts ſhoot from a reſt to a dead mark, and ſildom or never miſs: This Court runs and ſhoots at a flying mark, and therefore it is admirable if it ever hit aright. I ſay Sir, We come not to criminate, or to force a ball into the Dedan, but if any brick-wall expreſſions happen, that cannot be deſigned otherwiſe, it is rather a force upon us.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, upon the ſerious obſervations they have made of the proceedings of that Court, have made this judgment, That without ſome ſpeedy Rules and Inſtructions be given to thoſe Gentlemen, as the line and plumm to direct the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part of that great Act of Settlement, that the Lands juſtly forfeited to His Majeſtie, upon the account of that late horrid and unnaturall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in this Kingdom, and by His Majeſtie freely granted to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (to improve and enrich, which they have beggard themſelves) will be taken out of their poſſeſſion, and themſelves, wives and children expoſed to mockery and miſery; and actual Rebels that yet ſurvive, or the Heirs and Blood of thoſe that died actve in that Rebellion, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the ſame; and this being all done under pretence of ſevere ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the Roman Catholicks of this Kingdom, may get a reputation and credit to thoſe pamphlets they have diſperſt through <hi>Europe,</hi> That His Maſties Proteſtant Subjects firſt fell upon and murthered them. Sir, the Commons cannot but be apprehenſive of theſe coniequenſes, and therefore in this Inſtrument, have drawn certain propoſals by way of humble advice tendred to your Grace, in the name of the Commons of this Kingdom: They are not of the nature to impoſe any forraign ſenſe upon the Act, they ariſe out of the bowels of it; they ſeek not to lay out a new way, but only where ſome corners and deſtowers are, to hang out lights; and the greateſt Courts of Judicature will put out ſnuffs, when to read the Statute, they may have a Parliament-light, eſpecially a light held by that Parliament that paſt the Act: They have likewiſe their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy to your Grace, by a particular clauſe in the act requiring the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to give an account to your Grace and the Council, of their proceedings, to and follow ſuch further directions as they ſhall from time to time receive from your Grace and Council perſuant to the Act.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93645:4"/>
            <p>I ſhall crave your Grace's leave and patience to read it in diſtinct Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs, and according to the commands of the Houſe, to hint ſome parts of their ſenſe, for the reaſonableneſs of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Foraſmuch as by the Act of Settlement, there is a power veſtd in His Grace the Lord Lieutenann and Councel, to give further Directions and Rules from time to time, to the Commiſſioners for executing the ſaid Act; and foraſmuch as it evidently appears to the Houſe of Commons, That there is a neceſſity of ſeveral Rules and Directions to be given the ſaid Commiſſioners, therefore the following particulars are to be offered to the conſideration of his Grace the Lord Lieutenant and Councell, as the humble advice of the ſaid Houſe in order thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, though it ſounds as a preamble or introduction, and ſo may be lookt on as a Frontice-piece or Title-page by ſome; yet by us is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as an eſſential part of the ſtructure: If our diſtractions were doubled, they could not divide us in our duty. <hi>Nec natura aut Lex operantur per ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> you were not onely the neareſt port, but <hi>Statio bene fida carmis:</hi> And though the night ſhould grow dark, and tempeſtuous upon us, your care hath hitherto been as a Beacon upon a nigh Promontory, not only burning upon the arrival of a Fleet (ſuch as this Addreſſe is) but even to ſecure the leaſt Fiſher-boat, the ſmalleſt and individual intereſt, when it lays its courſe to you: Suyreme Councils, and General Aſſemblies, have, upon created or imaginary neceſſities, gone to the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> and having taken their obſervations from their own <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi> inſtead of the Guards of <hi>Charles</hi> his Wain, have arrived at <hi>Tyber</hi> inſtead of <hi>Thames:</hi> Now, Sir, being in our right Port, we ſhall break Bulk; and the firſt Propoſal is this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the King be by the Court of Claims allowed to be Party, as by Law he ought to be; and that no cauſe be brought to Adjudication, till the Attorny Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne rall have a fair Summons, and be fully heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Grace might think us under ſome diſtemper to offer this; for <hi>utrum nix ſit alb a, non est diſputandum:</hi> But if the Commiſſioners have declared in Court, That His Majeſtie is not concerned, and have, before judgment given, refuſed to admit evidence upon record, offered by Mr. Attorny-General in His Majeſties behalf, pregnant with evidence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93645:5"/>to have proved the Nocency of the perſon, and thereupon have declared the Nocent, Innocent, and in a breath blown down the Title of ſeveral Proteſtants, and their reſpective Heirs, their improvements, and the like, it is the Duty of Us ſitting in Parliament, judiciouſly having taken cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance thereof, to offer ſome Expedient againſt it. Sir, <hi>Innocent,</hi> or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> is the Queſtion, which without any help of a <hi>Septuagint,</hi> is tranſlated at the Bart of the Kings-Bench, <hi>Are you guilty of the general Rebellion of</hi> Ireland, <hi>or not? Stamf. pl. Cor.</hi> 1. I wonder if they will not infer this, <hi>inter placita Coronæ:</hi> Then under what Title would they refer it? If the Commiſſioners be pleaſed to conſult their Oath preſcribed by the Act, it is thus: <hi>Act. p.</hi> 59.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu ſhall ſwear, That you ſhall to the beſt of your skill, truly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially adminiſter Justice between his Majeſty and the Subject, and between party and parties, in the place of a Commiſsioner, for putting in execution His Majesties gracious Declaration and Inſtructions for the Settlement of</hi> Ireland, <hi>according to an Act intituled,</hi> An Act, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Oath is framed <hi>in terminis,</hi> according to the exigency of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter cognizable in every Claim by the Commiſſioners; for every Claim, Guilty, or Not guilty of the Rebellion, is one part, and hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been firſt tryed by them; and to this part, the Oath provides in theſe words, <hi>You ſhall truly adminiſter Justice between his Majeſty and the Subject:</hi> Then admit the perſon be adjudged Innocent, yet the Engliſh-Adventurer or Souldier, in caſe ſuch Innocent's Title to the Land be not good, is in by the Act; and then in the ſecond place, the Title comes in queſtion, and for this the Oath is ſuited, <hi>viz. And betwixt party and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Regularly, either by Office or Attainder, forfeited-Lands are veſted in the King, and his Majeſty being graciouſly pleaſed not to proceed by the ſeverity of Attainder, which reacheth life and corruption of bloud on the one hand, nor the expence and delatorineſs of Offices to be found, (not conſiſting with a Kingdome gaſping for a Settlement.) was pleaſed to reſt his Title upon a Tryal of Innocency: So that, exclude his Majeſty to be party, the Commiſſioners Judgments cuts both ways: The Iriſh are turned out of their Inheritances upon the account of Treaſon, and the King not party, the Engliſh ſhall have their Lands, and yet they were never legally ſettled in the King; ſo that Treaſon will ſeem to be a crime
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93645:5"/>not ſo much againſt the King, as againſt the Subject; Lands by the Act, are veſted in his Majeſty, ſo they be not the Lands of Innocent perſons, (and Qualifications for the tryal of their Innocency are poſitive.) Lands are given to the Adventurers and Souldiers, if they belong not to Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, where reſts the Freehold, in the Innocent perſons? That is but conditional and contingent; Is it in the Adventurer or Souldie? that is but conditional and contingent; Is it in the King? it is there but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional and contingent: Why then it is in <hi>cuſtodia legis,</hi> to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe three perſons; the Innocent can never have it if it be judged for the King, the Engliſh can never have it, except it be judged for the King: then to exclude the King is in conſtruction of Law, to exclude the Engliſh; for the Commiſſioners Decree cannot give the Land to the Engliſh, except the Act and Law warrant it, but nothing by Law can paſs from the King, till it be firſt in him, and there is no way by the Act to place it in the King, but by the judgment of the Court, betwixt the King and the pretending Innocent.</p>
            <p>Courts of Juſtice, <hi>ex Officio,</hi> if a title upon the pleadings ariſe for the King, are to take notice of it and improve it, though the King be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Action. <hi>Hob.</hi> 126.127.</p>
            <p>The Court will award a Writ for the King where the Title appears for Him on the Verdict, though the Iſſue find it not for him. <hi>Hob.</hi> 118, 119.</p>
            <p>And where Statutes are made to put things in an Ordinary form, and authorize inferiour perſons for the execution of it for the eaſe of Soveraign power, or the eaſe of the Subject, yet they ſhall never reſtrain the Soveraign power or Intereſt. <hi>Dyer,</hi> 225. <hi>part</hi> 35. <hi>Hob.</hi> 146.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this Act is a general Act as to this; nay, it is rather <hi>Statutum generaliſſimum.</hi> It concerns the King in giving and taking, which are relatives, and the Honour and Juſtice of the King in performing really the intents of his Grants doth as truth concern Him and His People, as doth His profit in enjoying and receiving Grants from them, (they are the words of a reverend Judge, the Lord <hi>Hobbart,</hi> whoſe ſpirit in the behalf and intereſt of the King; I would propoſe as imitable and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary to the Commiſſioners, I ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſyllable of his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, (the Caſe is <hi>Sheffield</hi> verſus <hi>Ratcliffe. Hob,</hi> 335.) (viz.) <hi>I muſt profeſs,</hi> that whenſoever I have thought of this Caſe, and adviſed upon it my ſelf, <hi>I have met</hi> with two ſtrong affections, Zeal and Indignation, Zeal in behalf of the King, <hi>to preſerve</hi> the ancient right of the Crown, againſt the invaſions of <hi>Rebells</hi> and <hi>Traitors;</hi> Indignation when I find
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93645:6"/>
               <hi>Francis Bigod,</hi> that ſometimes brought a <hi>puiſſant</hi> Army into the Field, to depoſe the King; failing in that enterpriſe, now to riſe <hi>up in judgement</hi> againſt him: that whom he could not by the Sword deſtroy, he <hi>might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant</hi> by the Law: For though <hi>Ratcliff</hi> bear the name of this Caſe, <hi>yet I ſee</hi> nothing, but the Land of <hi>Francis Bigod,</hi> his State, his Right, and Title, <hi>his bloud,</hi> his diſcent that maintain and defends it: Therefore let it not ſeem ſtrange, that <hi>I am warm</hi> in this Caſe, for Zeal and Indignation are fervent Paſſions: And <hi>I do profeſs,</hi> to give Prerogative to the right of the Crown in my care and vigilancy; and it is <hi>nobile officium Judiciis &amp; debitum,</hi> due by Oath and Office to watch for him, who <hi>wakes</hi> for us, <hi>Ne quid detrimenti Reſpublica capiat:</hi> And if Charity begin at it ſelf, <hi>ſo ought</hi> Juſtice to do, that the King, who granteth Juſtice to all, ſhould not be wanting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> This needs not by an Application to be ſhaken together, it mingles with the preſent purpoſe, as water doth with water; I ſhall onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the breath of this Reverend Judge perfumes the preſence Chamber: whatſoever is contrary in the like Caſe, is like the ſtench of <hi>Mare mortuum,</hi> that ſtifles whatſoever approaches it. This <hi>Francis Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god</hi> was attainted and executed, 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. And this zealous expreſſion was 13 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> by computation ſomething longer then from the 23 <hi>Octob.</hi> 41, to 1662. <hi>Bigod</hi> is reſolved into his firſt duſt, and thoſe dormitories have ſome priviledge, <hi>De mortuis nil niſi bonum,</hi> when the perſons with whom the preſent Iſſue is to be joyned, are living, <hi>vivit, imo vivit, etiam in ſena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum venit;</hi> The Queen 24. of her Raign, granted the ſame Lands to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Lord <hi>Sheffield,</hi> and the Reverend Judge, and the Court retreated not to the Objection made by our Commiſſioners, That the King had parted with the Lands from himſelf, and ſo in a manner <hi>qui poteſt capere capiat,</hi> thereby to render that great Act of Settlement, the Emanation of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royal Bounty, to be diſpenc't by a Rule of Juſtice, to ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a muſs of Apples or Nuts thrown in the Streets, to invite Boys to ſcramble.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Point, I ſhall crave leave to intimate to your Grace's remembrance, (for truly if I ſhould ſeek in this Point to inform your judgment, I were under an unpardonable guilt,) the opinion of his late Majeſty of ever bleſſed memory, how far he concerned himſelf, and the diſpenſation of his Juſtice,
<note place="margin">Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</note> in order to the Settlement of this Kingdom intereſted: In his Majeſties Speech delivered to both Houſes 14 <hi>Dec.</hi> 41. there is this expreſſion; But ſtill ſeeing the ſlow
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93645:6"/>proceedings therein, and the daily diſparities I have out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of the lamentable eſtate of my Proteſtant Subjects there, I cannot but again ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly recommend the diſpatch of that expedition unto you; for it is the chiefeſt buſineſs that at this time I take to heart, and there cannot (almoſt) be any buſineſs, that I can have more care of: I might now take up ſome of your time in expreſſing my deteſtation of Rebellions, in general, and of this in particular; To conclude, I conjure you by all that is, or can be dear to you and me, that laying away all Diſputes, you go on chearfully, and ſpeedily, for the reducing of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Majeſtiees anſwer to a Petition of the Parliament, his Majeſty delivereth himſelf thus:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>exact. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</hi> p. 34.</note> We cannot but thank you for this care, and your chearful ingagement for the ſuppreſſion of that Rebellion, upon the ſpeedy effecting whereof, <hi>The Glory of God</hi> in the Proteſtant Profeſſion, the ſafety of the Brittiſh there, our Honour, and that of this Nation, ſo much depends; all the Intereſts of this Kingdom, being ſo involved in that buſineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Majeſties Declaration to all his loving Subjects, publiſht with the advice of his privy Council, it is thus declared: <hi>viz. And our hope is, that not onely the Loyalty and good affections of all our loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will concur with us in the constant preſerving a good underſtanding betwixt Us and our People; but at this time, their own and our Intereſt, and lamentable condition of our poor Proteſtant Subjects in</hi> Ireland, <hi>will invite them to a fair intelligence and unity amongst themſelves, that ſo we may with one heart intend the relieving and recovering that unhappy Kingdem, where thoſe barbarous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels practice ſuch inhumanities, and unheard of outrages, upon our miſerable People, that no Chriſtian ear can hear without horrour, nor Story paralel;</hi> And a few lines after follows theſe words, <hi>(viz.) Whereas We acknowledge it a high Crime againſt Almighty God, and inexcuſable to our good Subjects of our three Kingdoms, if we did not to the utmoſt imploy all our powers and faculties to the ſpeediest and moſt effectual aſſiſtance and protection of that diſtreſſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And we ſhall now conjure all our good Subjects, (of what degree ſoever) by all the bonds of love, duty, and obedience, that are precious to good men, to joyn with us for the recovery of the Peace of that Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In His Majeſties Meſſage, ſent by the Lord Chamberlain to the Houſe of Peers, it is thus ſaid: <hi>His Majeſty being very ſenſible of the great miſeries and diſtreſſes of His Subjects in the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>which do daily increaſe ſo faſt, and the bloud which hath been alreddy ſpilt by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſneſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93645:7"/>and cruelty of thoſe Rebels crying out ſo loud,</hi> &amp;c. And in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>exact col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</hi> 34.</note> of <hi>Jan.</hi> 41. <hi>inter cætera; We have authorized our Juſtices of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and other our chief Governour or Governours and General, or Lieutenant General of our Army there, and do hereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, require and authorize them, and every of them, to proſecute the ſaid Rebels and Traytors with Fire and Sword, as perſons who by their high Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty againſt Us their lawful and undoubted King and Sovereign, have made themſelves unworthy of any Mercy or Favour,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In an anſwer of his Majeſties, are theſe words, <hi>viz. His Majeſty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more tender in that particular which hath reference to</hi> Ireland, <hi>as being moſt aſſured, that he hath been, and is from his Soul reſolved, to diſcharge his duty (which God will require at his hands) for the relief of his poor Proteſtant Subjects there, and the</hi> utter rooting out <hi>of that Rebellion. Exact Collect.</hi> 72. Thus far this glorious Martyr; and theſe are but few of many.</p>
            <p>But Sir, If any ſhall object, To what purpoſe ſerves this? A Rebellion is not diſputed, neither is there any that ever queſtioned His Majeſties abhorrence of it. I anſwer, Though ſeveral Pamphlets ſwarm, to faſten the rice of the Rebellion upon the Proteſtants, and that we drew the firſt blood, and much of the like ſtuff: yet theſe places are not quoted to that purpoſe, it is but to ſhew how unreaſonably His Majeſty is denied to be a party in diſcovering who were guilty of that Rebellion, ſo horrid and odious to all Chriſtians, to uſe His Majeſties words in another place, <hi>Exact Collect.</hi> 71. when eſpecially this very tryal of Innocency and Nocency, is the onely way preſcribed by the Act to veſt the Lands in the King, and is to ſupply the defect of Attainder and Offices to be found, which muſt be in the Kings name; or that any Commiſſioners can ſtrain the Act and Qualifications, to let Nocency be ſhrouded under Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and Treaſon to become merit. Beſides, it is to be obſerved, the Actors, Abettors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> notwithſtanding this jubilee of Indulgences under our gracious Sovereign, ſtands yet unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, the puniſhment being left to the execution of this Act; and ſhall the King be excluded in the tryal, and not made party? I ſhall ſay no more, but certainly thoſe that are of that opinion, differ much in judgement from his late Majeſty, and his Majeſty that now is, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herits his Fathers Vertues with his Throne: Beſides, I ſhall put your Grace in minde, that the Agents of the Roman confederate Catholicks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93645:7"/>of <hi>Ireland,</hi> amongſt other their deſires in writing, deſired that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Council at Law, might be at large, and indifferent; but it would not be granted.</p>
            <p>I ſhall further offer the judgement of the Parliament in <hi>England, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 41. in their third Propoſal to his Majeſty, <hi>viz. That you would be pleaſed to forbear to alienate any of the forfeitod and eſcheatod Lands in</hi> Ireland <hi>which ſhall accrew to your Crown,
<note place="margin">Exact Collect. 2.</note> by reaſon of this Rebellion, that out of them the Crown may be better ſupported, and ſome ſatisfaction made to your Subjects of this Kingdom, for the great expences they are like to undergo in that War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not infer, that his Majeſties neceſſities or Revenues muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied or ſetled by the confiſcation of innocent perſons Eſtates; God forbid we ſhould put that leavon into the Kings Treaſury, or ſuch Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drakes into the pot: But Sir, God ſorbid on the other ſide, that Nocents, Nocents in ſo high a degree, ſhould for want of evidence, that the Law allows in the Kings behalf, ſhould be made Innocents, whereby his Majeſties Revenue ſo conſiderately ſetled in this Kingdom, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to nothing; and ſo the Protection we enjoy by his Majeſties Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (for ſo is our condition in this Kingdom) be diſſolved, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the miſery, the Proteſtant Families turnd out to the open Sky, to entertain him, whom upon the accompt of Rebellion, his Sword had conquered. It is further worthy of conſideration, that his Majeſty is not onely concerned in his Revenue, but by a ſtrict decreeing of juſt forfeitures, anſwers a debt his Majeſty hath been pleaſed to take upon himſelf, by his Letters from <hi>Breda,</hi> to the Army here under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Duke of <hi>Albermarl:</hi> The payment of that part of the Army in <hi>England,</hi> drew vaſt Treaſures, whileſt the forfeited Lands here, by a due execution of the Act, will diſcharge that debt: Be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the worthy Adventurers of <hi>England</hi> (of which intereſt, ſaith his late Majeſty, <hi>I am reſolved to be very tender</hi>) and I am fure, Sir, it concerns a Proteſtant Parliament to be tender of them: Should our ſins provoke God to viſit us with ſo ſharp a correction again, as he did in 1641. with what conſidence could we expect ſupplies from <hi>England,</hi> if former Adventurers, bottomed upon ſo ſtrong a ſecurity, ſhould after ſuch ſo long, ſo expenſive ſolicitations, be diſappointed. And Sir, we are upon the precipices of this ruine, when amongſt all the perſons that have been reſtored as Innocents, we cannot underſtand of one, neither
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93645:8"/>can We ſay upon our own knowledge (and we come from all parts of the Kingdom) that any one of them, from 1641. to <hi>Sep.</hi> 165 — ever drew a Sword againſt the Iriſh in Rebellion, or ever aſſiſted the Engliſh forces in the proſecution of them: And much of this ariſeth, the <hi>King</hi> being not made party, by the vilifying of the Witneſſes produc'd by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, the checking of the Engliſh Council at the Bar, whileſt the inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Iriſh Counſel are paſt over in ſilence, the diſreſpect unto De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, Evidences, and the abſolute rejecting of other matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, His Majeſty we hope by your Grace and Council, being thus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his right: we come to the ſecond Propoſal his Evidence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all Examinations and Depoſitions whatſoever, taken for diſcovery of the Rebellion, as proceedings of the Rebels and their Adherents, as well du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his late Majeſties reign, or in the time of the uſurped Authority. All Books, Rolls and Writings, remaining in any Offices belonging to the Court of Claims, or in any of his Majeſties Courts of Record, as alſo the Books of</hi> Kilkenny, <hi>be taken for good evidence, in behalf of his Majesty, to bar ſuch perſon or perſons of their Ianocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, We promiſe the King to be party, and then this Propoſal reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but to evidence concerning Guilty or not Guilty of the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland;</hi> But in the general, as to evidences and proofs. We muſt take notice that the Law diſtinguiſheth times, and according to Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſuits and applyes its remedies; This is the great deſign of the Statute-Law, to alter and change the garments of the Law, according as the dimenſions of the Body Politique alter and change; The Notorie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Rebellion no Hiſtory can paralel, (to uſe his late Majeſties words) and yet to come to the proof of individual perſons acting in it, is no eaſie matter. In the late Wars between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> puiſſant and numerous Armies have been drawn into the field, and yet how few indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual perſons by exact proof of the adverſe party, could be concluded to have ever been preſent at any of thoſe battels? Our Caſe differs not; We were as diſtinct enemies as <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> under his Majeſties Government, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> under a Supreme Councel, and general Aſſembly. How can we witneſs without ſeeing? how could we ſee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fighting? during which Act, Our ſpirits on both ſides exerciſed not ſo much the reflect Act what We ſhould do hereafter before the Judge,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93645:8"/>as the direct Act, What we were to do upon the place before our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silent leges inter arma,</hi> was never more truly applicable, did our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition bear analogy with Nets and Routs in time of peace, the Law enabled us by means to maintain a diſtinct proof: But Sir, It is a true Maxim, <hi>Quod remedio destituitur, ipſa re valet ſi culpa abſit.</hi> and the Law where the ſubject matter in demand will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of proof,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Bulstr.</hi> 310.</note> will ſupply it, denying to deliver the money, the Law will conſter it a ſufficient proof to maintain a converſion of it; And the great Act of Settlement had in its proſpect theſe difficulties, the <hi>Act</hi> words (<hi>p.</hi> 4.) are <hi>viz. And for aſmuch as the Rapines Deprædations &amp; Maſſacres, committed by the ſaid Iriſh and Popiſh Rebels and Enemies, are not onely well known to this preſent Parliament, but are notorious to the whole World,</hi> Notwithſtanding <hi>the many</hi> Means <hi>and</hi> Artiffices, <hi>which for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have been uſed, to murther ſuch Witneſſes, ſuppreſs ſuch Evidences, and alſo to</hi> Vitiate <hi>and</hi> Imbeſil <hi>ſuch Records and Teſtimonies as might prove the ſame againſt particular perſons,</hi> &amp;c. Thus your Grace obſerves the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King and Parliament, that this is an extraordinary Caſe, and it is not diſagreeable to Law, <hi>Novis injuriis emerſis nova apponere remedia,</hi> and We ought not to allow that imperfection in our Law (living in the moſt glorious Conſtitution in the known World,) that Treaſon and Rebellion ſhould paſs with impunity; becauſe though the Law meets with theſe Enemies, <hi>per ſe,</hi> yet that it ſhould ſuffer them to eſcape, nay, to triumph, <hi>per accidens;</hi> No Sir, the Law will do much, <hi>ne curia Domini Regis deficiat in juſtitia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, more particularly; The Law betwixt party and party, allows in many caſes, Examination to be taken, <hi>in perpetuam rei memoriam;</hi> If ſo, it would be a hard conſequence of his Majeſties and Council, fore-ſeeing the difficulty of proofs, <hi>flagrante bello,</hi> ſhould authorize perſons to receive Examinations that then might be had, if afterwards no uſe ſhould be made of them; It is as true; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rex non præcipit inutilia,</hi> as that <hi>Lex non præcipit inutilia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cro. Car.</hi> 69, 70.</note> It is a remarkable Caſe of Sir <hi>Randolph Crew</hi> (ver. <hi>George Vernon:</hi>) That Examinations of Witneſſes taken by Commiſſion, after the death of K. <hi>James,</hi> (which Commiſſion le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally was determined,) yet ſhould be allowed to be goods eſpecially (as the words of the Judges are) in a Court of Equity, where the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are <hi>jure naturali,</hi> and not according to the ſtrict courſe of the Law; And be pleaſed to obſerve their further Reaſon certified to his Majeſty,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93645:9"/>
               <hi>(viz.)</hi> Otherwiſe it would draw into queſtion many tryals by verdicts of <hi>Niſi prius,</hi> and Tryals and Attainders upon Goal-deliveries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon divers have been arraigned and executed ſince the Kings death: ſo that your Grace may obſerve the prudence of the Law, to obviate incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, and therefore <hi>multa conceduntur per obliquum quæ non conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur in directo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Law requires not the attending of circumſtances ſo præ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe from matters given in evidence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kelway</hi> 166.</note> as it doth from the ſame matters by way of pleading;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Br. Records</hi> 65. <hi>ſtyle</hi> 34.</note> A man ſhall not plead a Record except it be in the ſame Court where it remains, unleſs it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified under the great Seal,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heatiey</hi> 138.</note> but otherwiſe, it may be given in evidence; A canceld Deed, (after teſtimony given of the matter of fact how it came to be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nceld,) was read in evidence: Proofs by depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition taken in the Exchequer in a former ſuit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lane</hi> 110.</note> ſhall be allowed, notwithſtanding the parties are alive: <hi>a fortiori,</hi> depoſitions taken in the Kings caſe, and between the ſame parties as in our caſe it is:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hob.</hi> 109.110.</note> But true it is, where the Kings Plaintiff, and the Defendant claims by Feoffment, and to prove it duly executed, deſire ſome depoſitions taken at <hi>York</hi> might be allowed, the Court refuſed it, becauſe the original of the depoſitions were gone ſo, as the King muſt fight with weapons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him by his adverſary;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Godbolt</hi> 439.</note> ſo if the Plaintiff cannot find his witneſſes to give teſtimony <hi>viva voce,</hi> then he is, as it were, dead unto him and his depoſitions in an Engliſh Court betwixt the ſame parties, may be read to the Jury.</p>
            <p>It is further obſervable, that in Tryals the Law allows evidence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the neceſſity of the ſubject matter: If the Lord diſtrain for Eſcuage, and the Tenant pleads, that he was with the King in <hi>Scotland,</hi> it ſhall be tried by the Certificate of the Marſhal of the Kings Hoſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Littelt. ſect.</hi> 102.</note> If in avoydance of an Outlawry, it is alledged he was at priſon in <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> it ſhall be tryed by the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the Major of <hi>Burdeux:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 74, <hi>Moor</hi> 451.</note> The iſſue was upon full age, and two Church Books were given in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected, That it would ſeem hard that Depoſitions taken by uſurp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Authority ſhould be good. I anſwer, The ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that warranted judicial proceedings in thoſe times to be confirmed, may allow theſe, onely the reaſon is ſtronger in our caſe, becauſe the matter of fact hath been ſo ſhifted, that the truth can appear no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93645:9"/>way: To this I add, That by the Act of Settlement they are allowed; the words are theſe, <hi>And whereas ſeveral of your Majeſties Subjects, by whom as Inſtruments, the ſaid rebels were totally ſubdued, dyed in the time of your Majesties abſence beyond Seas,
<note place="margin">Act Settl. p. 2.</note> (be pleaſed to obſerve, this was in the time of the uſurped Power) for ſupply of the then preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing neceſſities, and to prevent the further deſolation of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Kingdom (here</hi> neceſſitas vincit legem;) <hi>Enquire into the Authors, Actors, and Abettors of the ſaid Rebellion and War, (and this was by Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Examinations,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>And after much deliberation amongſt themſelves, and advice from others had thereupon, did diſpoſſeſs ſuch of the ſaid</hi> Iriſh <hi>Popiſh Rebels of their ſaid Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, as they found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, and to be engaged in the ſaid Rebeltion or War, and did withall diſtribute and ſet out the ſaid Lands,</hi> &amp;c. Your Grace may obſerve in this Clauſe, here is the Guilt, the Proof, the Judgement, and Execution, concerning the Rebels Lands, and the date of thoſe proceedings, is, during his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties abſence; and yet this is laid as the Ground-work of that Clauſe, which veſts the Lands in the King: for all the Characteriſtical Letters of forfeited Lands, in the fourth and fifth pages ofthe Act of Settlement, are, the manner and ways of ſeiſing, ſequeſtrating, diſtributing, allotting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of thoſe Lands under that power: for either that way muſt have been obſerved, or otherwiſe, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> being a conſederated Body aſſociated by Oaths, eſtabliſht under a <hi>Democraty.</hi> And laſtly, conquered by Arms, muſt, and of right might have been, according to the Law of Nations, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in groſs; It is to be feared, the King will encounter many Deeds and Settlements, and lewd Witneſſes, it is but reaſon he ſhould defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his own that are juſt: And if out of Acts of Uſurped Powers, his Majeſty ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les the peace of his Kingdoms, it is but a part of Royal Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry; out of poyſonous Minerals, to extract a Cordial.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 3. <hi>That ſuch Proclamations, or any Act of State as have declared any perſon or perſons, and their Adherents, Rebels, before the Ceſſation in this Kingdom,</hi> 1643. <hi>by his Majeſties Authority, ſhall be good Evidence in the Kings behalf, againſt ſuch perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r perſons, to the Impeachment of their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, before his Majeſties Commiſſioners, for Execution of the Act of Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93645:10"/>
            <p>A Proclamation is part of the Kings Prerogative, and obtains in caſes of neceſſity, the force of a Law, and is therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times termed <hi>Lex temporis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.33. a</note> If the King proclaim a Tilting to be held, and one kills another in that Exerciſe, this Proclamation ſhall be good by Pleading, or Evidence, to excuſe the Felony: The King, by Proclamation, may inhibit the Subject to go out of the Realm;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>f. n. b. c.</hi> 85. <hi>c.</hi>
               </note> and if the Subject doth againſt it, it is a contempt, and he ſhall be fined; and ſince it is a Law to fine, it will be good Evidence to juſtifie it: It was no time for Sheriffs, in the ordinary courſe or Law, to make Proclamations, in order to Outlaries, when without an Army it was hazardous to march two miles from <hi>Dublin;</hi> His Majeſties Proclamation of the 1. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. invites them, <hi>to lay down their Arms, and forbear all further Acts of Hoſtility;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 34 <hi>Pag.</hi>
               </note> If this Proclamation from <hi>Mount-Geball</hi> will not take place, that from <hi>Mount-Gerezzin</hi> muſt. And we never yet received an inſtance, that any embrac't thoſe offer, of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but though his Majeſty hung out a white Flag, they advanc't one of red. I ſhall onely add this, that it ſeems reaſonable, that if his Majeſty by name declares <hi>J. S.</hi> to be a Traytor, and to be proſecuted with Fire and Sword; in ſuch caſe, if any good Subject ſhould deſtroy the ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> he ſhall be indempnified by the Proclamation, why then admit <hi>J.S.</hi> have eſcaped to this day, I ſay if no intervenient Act of Grace from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty obviate it, this Proclamation may ſorely impeach his innocency, that might have warranted me to take away his life.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 4. <hi>That where by any Order or Orders of the Houſe of Commons, ſince</hi> 1641. <hi>and before the firſt Seſſions of this preſent Parliament, any of their Members, upon the account of the Rebellion, have been adjudged to be rotten Members, and fit to be cut off, and have Ordered the Speaker of the ſaid Houſe to direct his Letter for the iſſuing out of Writs to ſupply their places: That ſuch Orders ſhall be allowed as good Evidence, to bar ſuch perſon or perſons of their innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is firſt to be obſerved, this extends no further then to the Members of their own Houſe: And your Grace may remember, the Parliament fitting ſeveral Seſſions after the Rebellion, ahd reaſon to enquire what became of the far greater part of the Houſe; they found many <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93645:10"/>murthered, the ways for travelling obſtructed, for ſuch as ſurvived; or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they were engaged in his Majeſties ſervice, for defence of this Kingdom; the <hi>Iriſh</hi> they expected after Order upon Order, with their names publikely affixt, whereupon they did conceive one or more Orders, expreſſing the names of ſuch perſons, who upon their own knowledge, were ingaged in the Rebellion. The Houſe of Commons is a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Grand Jury, its a good <hi>Billa vera</hi> they return: Their Orders are Records;
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 23.</note> and that appears alſo by 6 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 16. where the words are, <hi>viz. And the ſame Licence be entred on Record, in the Book of the Clerk of the Parliament appointed, or to be appointed for the Commons Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. And more directly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Accompt of the Tryal,</hi> p. 46.</note> in the point upon the Tryal of <hi>Harriſon</hi> the Regicide, Mr. <hi>Jeſſop</hi> was produced to atteſt ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Commons Houſe, Mr. <hi>Jeſſop</hi> being Clerk of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 5. <hi>That the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Quarters be aſcertained from time to time, until his Graces receſs in</hi> 1647. <hi>and that all Quarters not ſo aſcortained, be adjudged the Rebels Quarters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> The Qualifications are the Soul and Spirit of the Act, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Qualifications, that of living and enjoying their Eſtates, reall and perſonal, in the Enemies Quarters, is <hi>velut inter ignes Luna minores,</hi> it is the Elixir of them; and therefore till thoſe be aſcertained, from time to time, we are as in a Labyrinth, without a Clue: It is offered to be aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from time to time, for the motion of War is Planetary; and there were Ebb and Spring-Tides, according to the ſucceſs of the Armies. This will much expedite time, and abate the <hi>Alamode</hi> ſin of Perjury: it will anſwer much the Proceedings of the Common-Law, where a Prohibition lyes, when the Bounds of Pariſhes are in queſtion, when a queſtion is, Whether Lands be in ancient Demeaſn, it is tryed by the Books of Domeſday:
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Cro.</hi> 228. 5 <hi>H.</hi> 5, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 188.</note> This is the <hi>Shibboleth</hi> to diſtinguiſh an <hi>Ephraimite</hi> from a <hi>Gileadite;</hi> and the Bounds of the Brook <hi>Kidron,</hi> warranted the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Shimei.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93645:11"/>
            <p>Propoſ. 6. <hi>That where two or more perſons have claimed one and the ſame L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, by ſeveral Titles, that ſuch Perſons Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles be tryed and aſcertained before the ſaid Commiſſioners proceed upon the tryall of innocency of any or eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without this, it will reſemble ſome Games at Cards, where the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Defendant will aſſuredly have his Cards ruſt upon one hand or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for example, three, or four, or more, (for that is uſual) claim the ſame Lands; now their reſpective innocencies come firſt in tryal; if three of four be judged nocent, and one innocent, by agreement (to give it no other name) amongſt themſelves, the other Titles ſhall veſt in him, who obtaining his decree of innocency, ſhall carry the Lands, whereas <hi>re vera;</hi> the Title was not in him, and yet the Court (according to this unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Rule) excuſable, as to the Judgment, and the Proteſtants to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, who cannot have cognizance of ſuch privy and dormant Titles: This Propoſal anſwers but the Rule of enter-pleading in the Law, wherein to give one inſtance of many: Two ſeveral perſons being found Heirs to Land, by two ſeveral Offices in one County; it is doubtful to the King,
<note place="margin">8 <hi>E.</hi> 4.6.</note> to which of them he ſhall give Livery; and therefore before Livery ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be made to either, they ſhall interplead, that is, formerly tryed between themſelves who is right heir.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 7. <hi>That in all Claims, the Titles to the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, be firſt tryed; and that the Deeds of all Nocents be left in the hands of the Court, there to remain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What hath been offered to the laſt Propoſal, may (in part) ſerve to evince the conveniency, if not neceſſity of this: it hath its riſe from a Maxim in our Law, <hi>Frustra fit per plura, quod ſieri poteſt per pauciora;</hi> for if it appear, that the party hath no Title, the labour of Tryal of innocency is ſaved,
<note place="margin">8 <hi>Co.</hi> 167.</note> where it is probable, Witneſſes may ſtrain the Point ſo far, as to make themſelves nocent before God, to make another innocent before man; and it is but conſonant to the uſual proceedings in Law, that where it appears to the Court,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cro, Et</hi> 230.</note> upon the Plaintiffs own ſhewing, that he hath no Title, though the Defendants Plea may be vicious, yet
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93645:11"/>he ſhall never have judgement. Beſides, Sir, it is to be obſerved, That the Trial of innocency is by the Act of Settlement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted into the place of an Office ſound,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stamfor.</hi> 63, 64.38 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 18.</note> and ſo is in nature of traverſing an Office, in which caſe the Law is clear, that none ſhall be received to traverſe the title of the King, without making a title to himſelf.</p>
            <p>As to that part that deſires the Writings of Nocent perſons to be leſt in the Court, it cannot work a prejudice to them; for the Lands being adjudged againſt them, to what purpoſe will the Writings operate in their hands: But Sir, I correct my ſelf, they will have an operation; and this puts me in minde of a plain, but appoſite ſimilitude: Sir, in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have a cuſtom in the Winter, when milk is ſcarce, to kill the Calf, and reſerve the Skin; and ſtuffing it with ſtraw, they ſet it upon four wooden feet, which they call a <hi>Puck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> and the Cow will be as fond of this, as ſhe was of the living C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſhe will low after it, and lick it, and give her milk down, ſo it ſtand but by her: Sir, theſe Writings will have the operation of this <hi>Puckcan;</hi> for, wanting the Lands to which they relate, they are but Skins ſtuffed with ſtraw; yet Sir, they will low after them, lick them over and over in their thoughts, and teach their Children to read by them, inſtead of Horn-books, and if any venom be left, they will give it down upon the ſight of theſe <hi>Pitckan</hi> Writings, and entail a memory of revenge, though the Eſtate-tail be cut off: Sir, how little ſoever this may weigh, yet in the Government of <hi>Rome,</hi> when the <hi>Tarquins</hi> were put down, not onely all moneys and Sculptures that might retain their memory, were by publique ſanctions decried, but ſuch Innocents as retained the name, were forced to aſſume new ones: The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> remembred the fleſh-pots of <hi>Ægypt,</hi> when Manna was before them; but when they wanted water, they murmured.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 8. <hi>That where the Claimant claiming an Eſtate of Inheritance, hath not ſet down his title certain, in ſuch caſe, the Claimant ſhall be adjudged to claim in Fee-ſimple, and not otherwiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, To open this propoſal; matter of fact muſt be thus ſtated, The Iriſh put in their claims generally under ſuch expreſſion;, That he is ſeized as of a Demeaſn in Fee, or Fee-tail, or ſome other Eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in uſe, poſſeſſion, or remainder: This hath been excepted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93645:12"/>againſt, but it hath been over-ruled to be a very good form of pleading: indeed it is Sir, for one cauſe, to take away all probable means where by the Proteſtant Defendant, may maintain his Cauſe, it indangers him not onely to looſe his Land, but firſt to looſe his ſence; Thoſe Preſidents will inrich our Books of Entries, as the German word <hi>Plunder,</hi> did out Engliſh Dictionaries, whileſt it beggard our Nation. Beſides Sir, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>Oyer</hi> of any Deeds, hath been over-ruled by the Court, ſo that when according to the preſent proceedings, We come to know the Title of the Iriſh Clymate: We have no more time of defence, then the Fowl hath, that no ſooner ſees the Fire in the pan, but dies of the ſhot in the Body.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Law præſuppoſeth every man of full age, to know his title, what ſhall this be accounted but a ſtratagem? and thoſe fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are hardly tenable, when one ſtanding upon the lines of defence, may be ſhort <hi>per derriere,</hi> is certainly the Center of the Law; and therefore it ſayes, <hi>Oportet ut res certa ducatur in judicium:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bra. b.</hi> 2. 5 <hi>Co.</hi> 3.21.</note> certa eſse debet intentio &amp; narratio:</hi> Unhappy was that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in treſpaſs, <hi>quare clauſum ſuum fregit &amp; piſces ſuos cepit,</hi> which was judged vicious for not ſhewing the number or nature of the Fiſhes, when Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments that in the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Law, are more worthy then two Fiſhes that are ſold for a farthing, may be demanded and recovered under all the incertainties and diſguiſes that may be; But the readieſt way to make <hi>Sampſon</hi> to grinde, is firſt to put out his eyes.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 9. <hi>That where any perſon or perſons, have put in his or their Claim, before the former or preſent Commiſſioners, and after put in another Claim of a different Title, the best Title for the King ſhall be taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, It is uſual for Merchants to put off an old ſtuff under a new name and here is new ſtuff put off under an old name; This by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners is called a <hi>Retraxit,</hi> and if they pleaſe to make good the word as the Law underſtands it, no exception will be taken; for a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traxit</hi> is,
<note place="margin">21 <hi>c.</hi> 4.38. 8 <hi>H.</hi> 6.8.</note> when the Plaintiff or Demandant comes in proper perſon into the Court, where the Plea is, and ſaith, that he will not proceed any further in the ſame: now this will be a bar to the Action for ever, <hi>Qui ſemel actionem renunciaverit, amplius re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petere non potest;</hi> but this <hi>Retraxit</hi> is much like the <hi>Retraxit</hi> of a Ram or Goat, that retires to make his aſſault with a doubled ſtrength; Truly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93645:12"/>Sir, We know not upon what clauſe in the Act this proceeding is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted; The proceedings before the former Commiſſioners are allowed, true it is, that ſome Commiſſions that iſſued from them for valuation of Lands, in order to repriſal, are ſuſpended until a new valuation iſſue by the preſent Commiſſioners, and then the beſt return for the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is to be made uſe of; if it be objected, thoſe Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ims were put in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Declaration and Inſtructions, which by the Act poſſibly may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; It is eaſily anſwered, either the Act hath given them a new title, or it hath not: if it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h given them a new title, then they are in by the Act, and not by any former title; if it hath given them none, then their old title is that they muſt rely on; But admit an election be, the Law is clear,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Noy.</hi> 29.</note> and ſo reſolved, that there is no election a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 10. <hi>That no Claimant claiming by Innocency, ſhall be allowed to make any other Claim, in caſe he ſhall be adjudged Nocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, We muſt crave your patience to conſider this Caſe; And firſt, the Act of Settlement (omitting other diviſions,) divides the Iriſh into Innocents and Nocents, and there is but one ſubject matter, upon which, both theſe diſtinctions have their proſpects, <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> the recovery of their Eſtates; I ſhall grant, that election of Actions belongs to every Subject as his Birth-right;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dep.</hi> 20.21, 57.</note> but likewiſe it muſt be granted, that where he hath made his election, proſecuted it, and determined it, he cannot have recourſe to renew his election, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſuſpected, but extinguiſhed; I ſpeak this with this <hi>ſalvo</hi> that a perſon that by particular clauſe in an Act, hath an Eſtate granted unto him, he muſt take finally and <hi>ſub modo,</hi> as the Act ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Br remitter.</hi> 49.</note> and hath no election to claim upon any former or other right; The body of the Act is but conſonant herein to the body of the Law that delights <hi>finem imponere litibus,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h all circuit of action: If a man by his Deed granteth a Rent-charge, and the Rent is arrear, it is in the Grantees election to bring a Writ of Annuity or diſtrein;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Littl. Sect.</hi> 219.</note> but he cannot make his election but once; for if he recover in a Writ of Annuity he ſhall never after diſtrein, or if he doth diſtrein, and avow in a Court of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cord, he ſhall never after bring a Writ of Annuity, becauſe an Avowry in a Court of Record, being in the nature of an Action, is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of his election, before a Judgment given; <hi>à fortiori,</hi> after Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93645:13"/>
            <p>If a Wife be endowed <hi>ex aſſenſu patris,</hi> and the Husband dyeth, the Wife hath election either to have her Dower at Common Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dower</hi> 158.</note> or <hi>ex aſſenſu patris;</hi> but if ſhe bring a Writ of Dower at Common Law, and Count, albeit ſhe recover not, yet ſhall ſhe claim her Dower, <hi>ex aſſenſu patris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So if the Grantee bring an Aſſize or the Rent, and makes his Plaint, he ſhall never after bring a Writ of Annuity: Nay, when an Election is given to ſeveral perſons,
<note place="margin">10 <hi>E.</hi> 4.17. 1 <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 145.</note> there the firſt Election made by any of the parties ſhall ſtand.</p>
            <p>A man by his own wrong may loſe his Election, as if a Feoffment be made of two Acres, the one for Life, and the other in Fee; if the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offee maketh a Feoffment of both, the Feoffor may enter into which of then he pleaſeth, becauſe the Feoffee hath loſt his Election, 2 <hi>Co.</hi> 36.37.</p>
            <p>It is well known, that where many times in one caſe., the Law doth give a man ſeveral remedies, that by the folly of his Election, he may bar himſelf for ever, 1 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtit.</hi> 27. <hi>a. b.</hi> 279. <hi>a.</hi> Its at the Election of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue in tail, to enter, or to allow himſelf out of poſſeſſion, and bring his <hi>Formedon:</hi> its at my election, if one receives my Rent, if I will charge him with a Diſſeizin, and allow my ſelf out of poſſeſſion, and bring an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize, or have an Action againſt him. 1 <hi>Cro.</hi> 220. but I ſhall be bound up by that election, to the advantages, or diſadvantages that accordingly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it. So it is in the Claimants election, to claim by Innocency, or Nocency; but after Judgment given, he ſhall be concluded.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 11. <hi>That any perſon claiming as an innocent, ſhall after proof of the title, proceed to prove himſelf to have been faithful, and loyal unto, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have actod againſt his Royal Majesty, or his Father, before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant ſhall urge any Crimination, and that for defect of ſuch proof of innocency, the Claimant ſhall be adjudged Nocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very letter of the Act rules this point (page 17. of the Act.) <hi>viz. That all innocent Papiſts, being ſuch as ſhall prove themſelves to have been faithfull and loyal unto, and never acted againſt our Royal Father, or Our ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. The Evaſion, that this relates onely to innocent Papiſts of <hi>Convaught,</hi> will not hold, except by ſome Philoſophical Rule, we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93645:13"/>may aſcribe a particular malignity to the Climat of that Province: it is alſo agreeable to the rule of Law, <hi>Actori iucumbit onus Probandi,</hi> they are the Plaintiffs, and have Eſtates granted to them, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they prove themſelves innocent: There is an Objection, the Solution whereof will aboudantly clear this point: The Objection, is, <hi>Stabilitur præſumptio, donec probatur in contrarium,</hi> and therefore every of them ſhall by Judgment of Law be preſumed innocent. I will grant this to be regularly true, but <hi>Diſtinguenda ſunttempora:</hi> when the whole Kingdom is under the ſerenity and calm of peace, and his Majeſties Writs have their free courſe, every man ſhall be preſumed to be a loyal Subject: for what appearance is there to the contrary? But, if a part of the Kingdom ſhall riſe up in arms againſt their Soveraign, and aſſume a contradiſtinct Government, and in defence thereof maintain a War, and, which is worſe, a ceſſation, with detention of his Majeſties Forts, and the inheritance of his Subjects, <hi>Niſi</hi>— this latter being an act of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deliberation, and this by Oath of Aſſociation, and by the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt rules of confederacy, Who is it, that without the violation of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and reaſon, can Judge all or any of them innocent, till by diſtinct and authentique proof, they have ſeparated that guilt from themſelves, which for ſo many years unto blood they eſpouſed? Upon this conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be pleaſed to heare the words of the Act, for that is the Touch-ſtone of pure or adulterate Expoſitions; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas an unnatural Infurraction did breake forth againſt your Majeſtie's Royal Father of over Bleſſed numory, his Crown and Dignity, in this your Majeſtics Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>upon the</hi> 23 <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>in the year of our Lord God,</hi> 1641. <hi>and manifest it ſelf by the murthers and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many Thouſands of your ſaid Majeſtics good and Loyal Subjects; which afterwards umverſally ſpreading and diffuſing it ſelf over the whole Kingdom, feetled into, and became a formed, and almoſt Nationall Rebellion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The caſe being thus truly ſtated, it is eaſy to diſcern both from the nature of proof, being in the affirmative; and the advantage that they are to receive by it; That they muſt putify themſelves according to the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Law, before they can be admitted to offer in the Temples of Juſtice: And therefore the caſe will be much like, as where a bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall endeavour to avoid the bargain, by reaſon of the <hi>non-enrollment</hi> within ſix months: he muſt make manifeſt proof thereof, or elſe it will be preſumed that it was enrolled within the ſix months. 4. <hi>Co,</hi> 20. Sir
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93645:14"/>if an innocent perſon will endeavour to avoid my preſent Eſtate, upon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he was not guilty of the Rebellion (being a Roman confoederate Catholick, under which Title the War was maintained,) he muſt prove his Innocency, or elſe it ſhall be preſumed he was one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> Tenants in common of a Mannor; <hi>A.</hi> purchaſeth a Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenement mixt with the demeſne Lands which were not certainly known: <hi>B.</hi> brings a Writ <hi>de Partitione facienda,</hi> of the Mannor only: It was held by the Juſtices, That <hi>A.</hi> muſt prove the bounds of the Frank-tenement putchaſed: For the Jury ſhall be diſcharged if in conſcience they make Partition, <hi>de tanto quanto præſumitur &amp; dignoſcitur per præſumptiones &amp; veriſim lia,</hi> Dyer, 266. So, Sir, the Iriſh Claimant coming under that violent Preſumption of Nocency, if he will not prove the bounds of his actings and converſation during that War, the Jury (if there were one) or the Court as it is at preſent, are diſcharged, if they judg him nocent, if upon proof allowed unto him he cannot clear himſelf of that preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I ſay [that violent preſumption] becauſe the Act caſts it upon him, and <hi>Fortior eſt diſpoſitio legis quam hominis:</hi> Nay, that Act to which he himſelf is a party: ſo that every Iriſh Claimant that appears in the Court, the Law ſuppoſeth him to plead thus; I confeſs the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> was univerſally ſpread, and became almoſt National, yet whoſoever is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent amongſt us, and ſo can prove himſelf to be, muſt have his Eſtate without a previous repriſal, and not otherwiſe; I am an innocent. Pray Sir, admitting, that the King by no grant or engagement had diſpos'd of this perſons Eſtate, would you not judge that Court very complemental, that upon ſuch allegation would judg him his Eſtate without any proof; There is little of my Lord <hi>Hobart</hi>'s zeal and indignation in that Court.</p>
            <p>Beſides Sir, if this were an Impoſition, it is no other then what the natural Olive is ſubjected unto; Thoſe Officers that ever faithfully ſerved his Majeſty, called the 49 men, and then why ſhould the wild Olive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine? Before they can be admitted to ſtate their Arrears, they muſt prove in what Regiment, Company, Troop they ſerved, with a <hi>continuando</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſervice; And nothing is more practicable. In the Barony of <hi>Eviſhoan,</hi> there are above two thouſand Iriſh can bring hundreds of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to witneſs their civil demeanor, through the whole courſe of the diſtemper in this Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93645:14"/>
            <p>Propoſ. 12. <hi>That every Claimant doth ſummon the Owner or Defendant of the Land, or upon</hi> Affidavit <hi>made that he or his dwelling cannot be found, the Tenant and Attorney of the Defendant, and after ſuch ſummons, notice be given of the day of hearing the ſaid Cauſe, by poſting the name of the Claimant, and Liſt of Lands in the Court</hi> 30 <hi>days before the hearing in</hi> Leinſter, <hi>and</hi> 40 <hi>days in any of the other Provinces, and that the Commiſsioners be deſired to publiſh the Lists promiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A true Regulation in this particular of Summons and Proceſs of the Court, is of great importance; errors in this, are like faults in our firſt, decoction not to be remedied: Notwithſtanding the long experience, and curious obſervations of the ſettled Courts of Juſtice, in 21 <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 3. which with us was Enacted 10 <hi>Car.</hi> c. 12. we were forced to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to a Statute for the avoiding of ſecret Summons in real Actions: Courts of Equity adhere cloſe to their Proceſs; in Courts of Law they are fitted, according to the Nature of the Actions to which they relate: And it is apparant, if this Point be not aſcertained in a different way then, as now it is uſed, many perſons will be, as ſome already have been, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed out of their Eſtates unheard, notwithſtanding their greateſt vigilancy to defend them.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 13. <hi>That the Commiſsioners obſerve to proceed in the tryall of Claims of Innocents, onely in the reſpective Counties, according to the Priority heretofore publiſhed by themſelves: And where any ſuch perſon claims in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counties, that ſuch perſon be not heard, till the laſt County come to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, according to the forementioned order of Priority wherein he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That there be a Priority of Counties, and that Priority poſitively to be obſerved, is of abſolute neceſſity: It were very hard (dividing this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into thirty three Counties) to give them all the alarm at once, and to continue them on that duty, when but one quarter is attaqued; we ſhall out-bid the Winds uncertainty by a point, that ever wandring within 32 points. Every man comes with the Spirit of a Gameſter, fairly confident to win, that is, to have his buſineſs ſpeedily heard; the Engliſh are ſerved with Proceſs, who muſt appear, both Plaintiff and Defendant are drawn up, with their troops of Witneſſes (a ſort of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93645:15"/>that muſt not run in arrears) always ready to fight, but uncertain when the Court will give the ſignal: it will be charge and expence enough to both parties, when it is confined to a particular County, but without Priority the charge will encreaſe in proportion, as 1. is to 33.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond part, to <hi>poſt-pone,</hi> the trial of the claim out in ſeverall Counties, to the time of the trial deſigned for the laſt County: This will be a ſole expedient to prevent ſurprizes in hearing (no ſmall fate to the Engliſh Defendant) and of no prejudice to the Iriſh Claimant; or if ſo, it were <hi>de minimis,</hi> which, in ſo comprehenſive a Settlement is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: For example, If a man have but three Acres in the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and a thouſand pound <hi>per annum</hi> in the County of <hi>B.</hi> as much more in the County of <hi>C.</hi> which is ſet forth to ſeveral Adventurers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, when this priority of Counties, and poſt-poning of trial to the laſt County is eſtabliſht and publiſht, all the Defendants are ſecure, untill the tryal of the laſt County comes, and then the ſeveral three Counties make an united defence; whereas otherwiſe, if he ſlip into his tryal for his three Acres in the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and by a faint defence or otherwiſe, he be adjudged innocent, it is likely that Decree of once innocent, ſhall be always innocent as to recover the remainder of his Eſtate in the other Counties, that never had notice of his Tryal.</p>
            <p>Next, it were manifeſt injury to the King, where the tryall may be, when the firſt County, or laſt County, comes upon the Stage, to take away the right of Election from his Majeſtie, ſpecially accompanied with a palpable loſs and diſadvantage: It is yet the character of two great Generals, That one <hi>cunct ando,</hi> by delaying, recovered the loſt eſtate of the people; The other <hi>Celerando,</hi> by precipitation, loſt what was in poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 14. <hi>That matter of fact cognizable by the Court of Claims, be tryed by Jurors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not well underſtand, how by the Act any other way of tryall is allowed; for in ſome caſes, leſt there might be a miſtake of what proof is intended, it is particularly ſet down by Juries: Next, this Tryal by Juries, is the ancient way and birth-right of the people, <hi>State <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uper vias antiquas:</hi> And though this Act had Enacted a tryal otherwiſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93645:15"/>and onely in the affirmative, it would not have excluded or barred this ancient way of tryall by the Common Law, and which was before the Conqueſt <hi>(Lamb, verbo. Centur.)</hi> Beſides, it is the clear uncontrover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſtruction of the Law, that, Whereſoever a Statute mentions the word <hi>Proof,</hi> the Law intends it of no other mannor of proof whatſoever, then that by Juty. The Court of Chancery, how often doth it recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend iſſues to the tryal of the Common Law Courts by Jury. Matter of Law, and matter of fact are divided: to the firſt, the Judges anſwer; to the laſt the Jurors. Upon any wrong done by the Court, there lies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy by Error for the Subject; if by the Jurors, then by attaint; but as now the execution of this great Act ſtands, admit the Court being Judges both of the Law and Fact, will decree away my Eſtate, Where is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy? The higheſt Court of equity allows a Review: <hi>Hob.</hi> 202, 203. reſolved by the Judges, That to try cauſes that were naturally triable by the Common Law, and by the Jury, by a Chancery way, would ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealy confound all Juriſdictions, make all the Common Law, and all the courſe of it, needleſs, and a handmaid to the Chancery. It is further conſiderable, that this will certainly bring great prejudice to his Majeſties intereſt; for Jurors may finde many things, that the Court will not, or is not bound to take notice of, the finding whereof may veſt the Eſtate in the King: A verdict may finde matter of Record, which was never given in evidence; and ſo likewiſe matters of writings, and other things, not within the pleadings, or ever given in evidence; and nothing, can more contribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the juſt diſcovery of men, and their demeanors in theſe troubleſome times, than by the knowledge of their neighbours, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cini vicinorum facta præſumutnur ſctre:</hi> And there is no reaſon that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Intereſt having but one eye left them, as to this point of diſcovery, and that not yet recovered from the bloudſhed, ſhould have that put out: Sir, if no other reaſon moved, this would induce us, Leſt we caſt a diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute upon our ancint and known Laws, that make this Iſland a <hi>Terra fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> as if theſe ancient Courts were only Pleaſure-boats in fair weather, and could not ride it out in a ſtorm: Sir, if we ſettle the Kingdom by any other means, than by the experienced rules of thoſe Lawes, we may haſtily bring our wounds to healing and skinning, whileſt a <hi>ſanies,</hi> and corruption lyes at the bottom, which will break forth more incurable than at firſt.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93645:16"/>
            <p>Propoſ. 15. <hi>That no perſon ſhall be admitted to prove his Innocency by any other Witneſſes, then ſuch as have conſtantly lived in the Engliſh Quarters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt with your Grace's favour conſider the iſſue again, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Guilty or not Guilty of the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland;</hi> if ſo, no perſon that is <hi>Particeps criminis,</hi> that is under the ſame guîlt, ought to be admitted a witneſs againſt the King to prove the perſon upon his Tryal innocent, <hi>Facinus quos inquinat, æquat:</hi> If a perſon be <hi>infamous,</hi> if he be attainted of a falſe verdict, or conſpiracy at the ſuit of the King, or convicted of perjury or of felony, whereby they became <hi>infamous,</hi> or regularly he that loſeth <hi>Liberam legem,</hi> cannot be a witneſs; now if your Grace conſider what hath been hinted formerly, how the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and owned by confoederacy, aſſociation, by their repreſentatives in the General Aſſembly; that were <hi>Homines generici,</hi> as Divines term <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> when by his fall his poſterity fell: If your Grace reflect upon the ſpreading conſequences of it, that as it was voted by power, and truſt ſent from all the Counties, Cities, and Burroughs, within their power, ſo it was tragically acted in every part of this Kingdom; And laſtly, if your Grace caſt your eye upon the mark, and level in this caſe, the Act of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, which upon theſe and other conſiderations, have called it uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and almoſt National: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would ſeem but very juſt that ſuch crimes ſhould not be purged by perſons guilty of the ſame, which all under that confoederacy by the Judgment of Law and that Act, are; Theſe perſoes have by their own induſtry loſt <hi>Liberam legem,</hi> their Eſtates are forfeited as well as if it were by Office or at tainder. For What? It is anſwered Upon the account of the Rebellion: then certainly the witneſs muſt be <hi>Rectus in curia,</hi> before he can make anothe ſo; for <hi>Quicquid efficit tale, eſt magis tale:</hi> in a <hi>modus decimandi,</hi> againſt one, the reſt of the Pariſhioners ſhall not be witneſſes; in defence of Common againſt a Commoner, the reſt ſhall not be witneſſes, <hi>Hob.</hi> 92. And yet the union and tie in theſe caſes, are not under ſuch ſtrict intereſt of aſſociation, as amongſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foederate Catholiques of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be objected, We make uſe of them againſt themſelves: It is eaſily anſwered, It is but juſt and reaſonale: A Tarryer is the only crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to unkennel a Fox, becauſe he is got by a Fox and a Brache hound; How is it poſſible for us to prove ſuch a perſon to have been at ſuch a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, to have contributed to their aſſiſtance, to have ſat in their General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93645:16"/>but by perſons frequent amongſt them, and of their own confoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, and ſuch a Witneſs is in Law a double Witneſs, and the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon urgeth the neceſſity of their proof by ſuch as lived in our Quarters: Beſides, it is known how the Law is, in caſe of an Approver, who though he confeſs the ſame Felony, <hi>Stamf.</hi> pl. Cor. fol. 142. Who either by direction of the Court, or at the prayer of the Felon himſelf, is examined by the Coroner, and his examinations taken upon Record for the good of the King and Commonwealth. And Sir, I ſuppoſe the Opinion is maintainable, (eſpecially as the proceedings are,) if he or they that were in arms in <hi>Munſter,</hi> are not equally guilty of the bloud ſhed by the Army in <hi>Ulſter:</hi> they move by joynt Counſels, from one publick ſtock of maintenance, the victory of one is the victory of the other, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the bloud ſhed by one, is the bloud ſhed by the other: It is good Law, that if a man received a man that is attainted of Felony by Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary in the ſame County, though he be ignorant of it, yet he is acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Felony, becauſe the Outlawry is matter of Record, of whſch every one ought to take notice; This were <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> a hard Law, if when an open and univerſal Rebellion is maintained, and the Kings Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours ſlying in the field, and the Sword, and other Enſigns of Royalty at home, (as notable matters of Record, as an Outlawry upon Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the County-Court,) that perſons ſhould not take notice of it, and then taking notice of it, ſhould relieve and abet the actors therein, and inſtead of being puniſhed as acceſſaries, they ſhall triumph, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to clear the principals, (if any acceſſaries, were in Treaſon,) The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Law why if 3. or 4. be in a room, and but one gives the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtroke, yet the other ſhall be acceſſaries, is, becauſe the preſence of the reſt abated the courage of him that was killsd to make his own defence: upon the ſame reaſon, all the confoederate Catholiques are acceſſaries or principals.</p>
            <p>If it had been underſtood by the Proteſtants in <hi>Ulſter,</hi> that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion had been only the attempt of Sir <hi>Philome,</hi> or a Rabble, as in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick papers the Iriſh have termed it, ſo much bloud had not been ſo cheaply ſpilt: but hearing it was univerſall, and countenanc't by confoederacie of all; that his Majeſties Proclamations to lay down armes were contemned, this abated their ſpirits, and made way for diſpair to dethrone reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93645:17"/>
            <p>Propoſ. 16. <hi>That when the Court doth give Judgment upon any cauſe, that every reſpective Commiſsioner</hi> ſeriatim, <hi>deliver his particular Judgment in open Court, with the reaſons thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, It is among the ornaments of our Law, that matters are very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly debated at the Bar, and in Cauſes of difficulty, ſolemnly argued by the Judges on the Bench; In every leaf of our Year-Books and Modern Reports, we may diſcern the Judges Opinions and their Reaſons. No doubt but Judicatures are under great temptations, and a greater check cannot be upon the frailty of our Natures, that they lie not under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of a concurrency: As true it is, that virtue hath been ſcandalized by an affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y with vice, ſo likewiſe it is true, that vice gets a reputation by a commerce with virtue: That <hi>Cato</hi> did look on, was held to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to ſome ſpirits; and no doubt but when ſo great an audience as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that Court, ſhall hear every particular Commiſſioners Judgment, and the reaſons of it, whether it may prove as a means of caution to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet ſurely it will give a great ſatisfaction to the perſons concerned, upon whoſe unintereſted Judgment they may repoſe as well, as upon their Councels argument: Thus it was in the caſe of Ship-money. And ſuch is the ſolemnity of Judgments, that they are en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red <hi>Conſideratum eſt per Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam;</hi> if it be entred <hi>Videtur Curiæ,</hi> for the levity of it, error will reverſe it.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 17. <hi>That where</hi> affidavit <hi>ſhall be made, that one or more materia Witneſſes being ſummoned before the Court, refuſe or neglect to come in, that ſuch cauſe be ſuſpended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Propoſal is the iſſue of Experience: for we are certainly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that divers perſons who have formerly offered themſelves as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and that have declared their knowledg in order to prove the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of ſeverall perſons, withdraw themſelves ſome alledge they are under the cenſures of Excommunic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions, and Fulminations, (they are hard words, but happily your Grace remembers them, when not only your Grace, but ſuch as ſhould give your Grace any relief, or thoſe that ſerved under your Command, have been involved in the ſame, and perchance your Grace hath not forgot the operation of them). It is ſaid in Philoſophy, <hi>Actus activorum non ſunt niſi in patiente bene prædiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito.</hi> How receptive the complexion of the people hath been of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93645:17"/>I ſhall paſs by; onely thus much I muſt obſerve, if they were ſo powerful as to violate the Bonds of Allegiance, to their lawful and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soveraign, they may without ſtraining, diſſolve the Reciprocations of Common Equity amongſt Subjects: Eſtates reſt upon Proofs, and if Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes neither <hi>flectuntur prece aut pretio,</hi> I mean their neceſſary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient expences tendred: we muſt reſort to the Law for its proceſs; If they will not mannage with a Snaffle, perchance their Heads may be brought into a Rane with a Port-pit: And, upon <hi>Affedavit</hi> made, it is but reaſonable to ſuſpend the Cauſe: There is no priviledge in this caſe by Law, to exempt them for giving Evidence in his Majeſties behalf, and for ſettlement of this Kingdom, which is the adæquate Object of the Act: There are no ſtronger or nearer Relations then Man and Wife, that the Law (in many reſpects) eſteems them as an <hi>Individuum:</hi> Yet a Wife, for the King, may be brought to give Evidence againſt her own Husband: <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegium non valet contrarempublicam:</hi> A Maſter of a Ship, laden with Merchants Goods, may caſt them over-boord; but if he be laden with Ammunition, Ordinance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Kings, to relieve his Army or Garti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he cannot juſtifie to fling them over-board, though the Veſtel and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners lives are at the ſtake, (<hi>Bacons ma.</hi> pag. 17.) But is not the ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lement of the Kingdom of more worth, (and that depends upon the faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of Evidence) then a particular Garriſon.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 18. <hi>That where any perſon or perſons provided for, to be reſtored by particular name to any Eſtate, that ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall not be admitted to claim the ſame, under, or by any other way or means, then is laid down in ſuch Clauſe in the ſaid Act, wherein he or they are ſo particularly named.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Grace, this humble Propoſal is one of the Poles, upon which the Act of Settlement moves; and it hath its particular aſpect upon the Clauſe, in <hi>page</hi> 21. of the Act, in which ſeveral perſons are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly named; and afterwards it is ſaid thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We do hereby declare, That they and every of them, without being put to any further Proof, ſhall be reſtored to their former Eſtates according to the Rules and Directions, in the laſt fore-going Clauſe of this Our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, concerning ſuch as continued with Us, or ſerved faithfully under Our Enſigns beyond the Seas.</hi> Now Sir, we have conſidered that fore-going Clauſe, <hi>VIZ. That ſuch perſons ſhall be reſtored to their former eſtate, a Reprize being firſt aſsigned, and legally ſet out of the remaining forfeited
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93645:18"/>Lands undiſpoſed of, to ſuch Adventurer or Souldier, or other perſon before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, of equal value, worth, and purchaſe to the Eſtate, out of which ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer or Souldier, or other perſon aforeſaid, ſhall be ſoremoved.</hi> So that it appears clearly, none of theſe perſons are intended by the Act to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without a <hi>prævius</hi> Repriſal firſt ſet out: And they are, as to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their Reſtitution, placed in the Catalogue of thoſe that ſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas under his Majeſties Enſigns.</p>
            <p>Though nothing can be clearer, yet Sir, be pleaſed to obſerve, how in order to the Deſign of this Clauſe, ſeveral other Clauſes in the Act are particularly framed for the execution of it. In <hi>page</hi> 26 of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> where the Rules of Precedencies in reſtitution were ſet down, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the proviſion made for ſuch as ſerved abroad, &amp;c. or otherwiſe they were totally left out: But it was but reaſonable, ſince their manner of Reſtitution was limited, according to the reſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution of thoſe that ſerved abroad, that they ſhould be included with them, and it had been meer ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſage to have men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioned them.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, to proceed, in <hi>page</hi> 37. of the Act, there is a particular Clauſe for the further making the former Clauſe practicable, <hi>viz. In the next place, you are to take care, that the Adventurers, Souldiers, or other perſons, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of any of the Estate or Eſtates of ſuch perſons, to whom We have by our ſaid Declaration aſſigned a particular favour, and are in a diſtinct branch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by Name expreſſed, be Repriſed, as in our ſaid Declaration is expreſſed, and the ſaid perſons reſtored to their former Eſtates, from the time that ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers or Souldiers ſhall be ſo Repriſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be pleaſed Sir to obſerve, leaſt this intimation might not be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory enough, it concludes, <hi>obſerving always the former cautions and proviſions in our ſaid Declaration expreſſed,</hi> referring to the ſaid perſons reſtoration: that is, (<hi>pag.</hi> 20.) <hi>A prævious Repriſal being firſt ſet out.</hi> One might think here were a particular Act of Parliament from themſelves, aſſertaining under what terms they were to enjoy their Eſtates. But in the percloſe of the whole Act, <hi>pag.</hi> 118, 119. <hi>Provided alſo and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That in caſe Reprtſals ſhall fall ſhort, whereby perſons mentioned and appointed in the ſaid Declaration and this Act, to be reſtored with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being put to any further proof.</hi> This is the Character (that denotes the ſame perſons, cannot or ſhall not obtain or receive the full benefit inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them) Sir, be pleaſed to obſerve, there was no other benefit intended them, <hi>then it ſhall and may be lawful for the Lord Lieutenant, or other chief Governour or Governours, and Council, for the time being, and they are hereby
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93645:18"/>authoriſed to order, appoint, and make distribution amongſt them, of the ſame ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction or reſtitution allotted them, in ſuch proportion and method as they ſhall judge moſt equal and juſt conſideration being had, of the conditions and pretences of the ſeveral perſons concerned: Nevertheleſs, according to the Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of the Declaration concerning them in all other Points, and particularly of that of</hi> Prævius Repriſe or Repriſals, <hi>which Order and appointment of theirs ſhall be final, and obſerved by the Commiſſioners appointed, or to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the execution of this Act; any thing therein contained to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> Thus Sir, your Grace ſees how the Intereſt of theſe perſons ſo named, is fenced and bounded throughout the Act; ſo that indeed, the final determination of their Intereſt cannot be adjudged; no, nor the Intereſt of any one of them aſſertained, till the value of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals appear before your Grace and Council, and then your Order ſhall be ſinal, and directive to the Commiſſioners: And it cloſeth home with <hi>Any thing contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though this be ſo, they are beginning to leap over the hedge, and putting in the ſtrongeſt fore-maſt, and wave all theſe Clauſes, and put in their Claims upon the account of Innocency, upon which, they had once an election to have relyed upon, but now it is determined by this Clauſe: The reaſon that induceth them is plain; for if they ſhould be judged In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents, then they are reſtored without any conſideration of Repriſal: If they be judged nocent, then they will keep this Clauſe for a Retreat.</p>
            <p>But Sir, I am commanded by the Houſe of Commons, humbly to offer your Grace their Opinion, that this is contrary to the whole courſe and reaſon of Law in the general, and very illuſory to the main Deſign of the Act; and in the opening this Point, I have command to be an humble Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to your Grace for your patience, his Majeſties In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereſt as to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, and the Proteſtants Intereſt, being ſo highly concerned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sir, We preſume it will be allowed, That an Act of Parliament binds all perſons, for all perſons are parties to it, 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.4. nay, my Lord <hi>Cook, Inſtitut.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 4. tells us, that multitudes are bound by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are not partie to the Elections of the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, as all that have no Freehold.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Freeholders in ancient Demeaſn.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All Women, having Freehold, or no Freehold.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Men within age, &amp;c. A <hi>fortiori,</hi> then thoſe are bound by this Act, to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93645:19"/>which they themſelves in perſon have given their aſſent. Now Sir, as to the point in hand, (<hi>viz. That the perſons that are by peculiar name reſtored to their Eſtates, under a</hi> prævious <hi>Repriſal, can claim them no other way then the Act preſcribes.</hi>) I ſhall humbly offer you the Judgment of the Sages of the Law in an inſtance or two: Where a man hath Title to Land by an Eſtate-tail; and afterwards the ſame Land is given to him by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Heir ſhall not be remitted, for by the Act of Parliament all other Titles are for ever excluded; for this is a Judgement of Parliament, that the Eſtate ſhall onely remain in the ſame very way that it is given: The ſame Law is, where the King hath a Title in Tail, and the Land is given to him by Parliament in Fee; the Eſtate-tail is determined, ſo that the Heir ſhall not avoid the Leaſes made by his Father; for the Statute binds all for Titles and Eſtates, <hi>B. Parliam.</hi> 73. The Reaſon given here, is, for that it is a Judgment in Parliament; and of what extenſive power that is, even to take the right hand of an Act, 2 <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 497. will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>Nay Sir, the operation of a Statute caſts it with that violence upon the party taking it, that if it had given me the Eſtate of any p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rticular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by name, ſaving the right of that party, the ſaving had been flattering (as we call it) 1 <hi>Co.</hi> 47. <hi>a. b.</hi> It is ſaid, Though the Act be in nature of a Conveyance or Judgment, the ſaving is repugnant, as to him that makes the Conveyance, or againſt whom the Judgement is given, or from whom the Eſtate of the Land is to paſs; for though they be parties to the Act, yet, in Judgement of Law, the Land ſhall move from him that is ſeized, (<hi>Plowden</hi> 49.) it is there held, where Lands are given by Statute, it ſhall be interpreted the gift of the Ter-Tenant, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all others that aſſent to the Act; for if it ſhould be adjudged the gift of another perſon, the Parliament ſhould do wrong to the Ter-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to take away the Land, and make another to give it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> The application is eaſie and familiar to your Grace, who well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members the great Solicitations that was made to get into this Clauſe; it was lookt on as the <hi>Ark,</hi> for thoſe who could not endure the <hi>Examen</hi> of <hi>Innocency;</hi> and being <hi>nocent,</hi> found themſelves bound by the Act, to be concluded, by taking out of Lands in <hi>CONNAUGHT,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of their former Eſtates; they very well underſtood, that the Gate of <hi>Innocency</hi> had no flaming Sword over it, to keep any from entring. As great and powerful Proviſions are made for ſuch perſons, as Wiſdom could contrive; but the Law preſuppoſeth, every man knowing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93645:19"/>own Eſtate and condition beſt, will not make an election to his preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; but if he do, and that election is executed by an Act of Parliament, he is bound for ever, <hi>Hob.</hi> 256. it is thus.</p>
            <p>Note, an Act of Parliament hath every mans conſent, as well preſent as to come, and he may be an Authour of his own hurt; alſo he muſt hold as the Act gives it, having power to bind every mans right, finally or <hi>Sub modo;</hi> and therefore if any perſon by his application to the King, when out of his Princely favour, hath granted his Requeſt, though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath re-intrencht himſelf of a proviſion otherwiſe held out unto him, he muſt lay his hand upon his mouth, and own the inconvenience to ariſe from himſelf; It hath been judged, that Licenſe for alienation by Parliament, takes away the Fine, otherwiſe by Law due to the King: The like in caſe of partition by Parliament between the Co-heirs of the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> 1 <hi>Le. pl.</hi> 113. the reaſon is given there, for that the Queen her ſelf is party and principal Agent, and therefore againſt her own Act, ſhe ſhall not claim the Fine; And ſhall an Act attatch the Revenues of the Crown, that <hi>are firmamentum belli, &amp; ornamentum pacis,</hi> and yet a private perſon avoid, and make illuſions a Statute, for which himſelf hath been a ſuiter; and to which, upon the paſſing of it, he hath perſonally given his vote:
<q>Ecce mode mirum —</q>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Nothing is more favoured by our Law then a Remitter, and even that upon conſtruction of the Stat. 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. that ancient priviledge of the Common Law is ſo over-ruled, that the perſon taking by the Statute, in moſt caſes, ſhall not be remitted: and if a Statute by conſtruction, layes aſide the indulgence of the Common Law in publick ſettlements <hi>à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori,</hi> it will bind private Intereſts particularly expreſt.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I muſt obſerve, That all the clauſes relating to theſe particular perſons, though they are in the affirmative, yet being directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as to the form and manner of their reſtauration, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhall be reſtored from the time that ſuch Adventurers or Souldiers ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>viz.</hi> obſerving always the further cautions and proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our ſaid Declaration expreſſed, reſerving to the ſaid perſons reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (<hi>pag.</hi> 38.12.19. <hi>Act</hi>) they carry in them a negative; for it is a Rule, That all Statutes that limit a manner and form in execution of matters that were not ſo by the Rules of the Common Law, though they be in the affirmative, they are in ſubſtance the negative, as if it had been expreſt, That it ſhall be done in the manner and form, and no otherwiſe; ſo it hath been adjudged upon <hi>West.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. that gives,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93645:20"/>
               <hi>Quod ei deferunt,</hi> and that the Demandants may <hi>Vocare ad warrantum as ſi eſſent tenentes,</hi> that is as much as if it had ſaid, <hi>Et nullo alio modo;</hi> and ſo 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 20. where it is ſaid, he ſhall enter, enjoy and poſſeſs the Land, according to his title in them, it ſhall be underſtood, according to his title, and in no other manner, <hi>Plowd.</hi> 113. Now to reſtore an Nocent, that is, one guilty of Rebellion, to his former eſtate, certainly will be granted, it is not agreeable to Common Law, why then when this Act particularly names ſome of them, and that under the character of Nocent perſons, and preſents the way, order and means of their reſtauration, not once, but through the texture of the whole Act, it muſt needs rationally follow, that it is intended, and no other way. The Act ſaith, <hi>You ſhall obſerve the Rules for their reſtauration:</hi> what is the Rule? it is this, after a <hi>previous</hi> repriſal; but if you take him out of this clauſe, and put him upon Innocency, then he is to be reſtored before a repriſal: I humbly ask, How is the Act anſwered, that ſayes, Thus it ſhall be: No, ſaith the Court, it ſhall be thus: And by ſaying ſo, a great part of the Act is made to ſignifie nothing (nay, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of the Act upon which the Proteſtant Intereſt wholly depends, for that being obſerved, they are ſure to have their penny, or pennyworth, the Eſtates they now enjoy, or repriſal which by the plain and genuine conſtruction, preſerves all the part of the Act in ſummetry and proportion; and I am ſure this was the Judgement of the Houſe, upon paſſing the Act: I ſhall ſhut up this point, with that which ſhould have had the preference, even the conſideration of his Majeſties Revenue; if the perſons be held to the clauſe of their own Election, they are to pay the ſame Rents the Adventurers and Souldiers pay by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre; if otherwiſe, their former Rents, which are not conſiderable: We know upon whoſe account it is, that his Majeſty is at that great charge to maintain an Army here, it is but reaſonable a round ſhare of the charge ſhould lie on them; whileſt the greateſt Eſtates of the Iriſh in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that are rationally qualified by this Act, if they eſcape it, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do beat the burthen, and they ſcarce touch it with their little ſinger.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 19. <hi>That the Officers before</hi> 49 <hi>and their Tenants, ſhall be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Witneſſes to give evidence for his Majeſty in any cauſes whatſoever, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending before the Court of Claims.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, We muſt remember again the Tryal, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Guilty or not Guilty, between the King and the party, and that in matter of Treaſon, which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93645:20"/>premiſed, I might ſay no more to evince the lawfulneſs of any of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects, to give Evidence upon ſuch a Tryal: I ſhall admit, that regularly no than ſhall be Witneſs in his own cauſe: but this is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood <hi>cum grand ſalis;</hi> It is ſaid in our Law, <hi>Judicis officium eſt ut res, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n tempor a rem quærere, quæſito tempore, tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us eris;</hi> I have hinted before how difficult it is for proof to be made, after ſo long a tract of time ſpent in War, and in confuſion, ſince 41. till his Majeſties happy Reſtoration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Act, ſaith the Witneſſes, have been ſlain, and thoſe few, the Officiers ſerving before 49. whom Providence reſerved, when God impanne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a Jury to enquire after bloud, muſt be challenged: The ways by which Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence might have been had, hath been by the power of the Sword drawn againſt, the Law been obſtructed; and therefore it may bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll to ſuch guilty perſons Exceptions. <hi>Fruſtra qui in legim peccat a lege petit auxillum:</hi> Were an unlawful Aſſembly, at this day, in a riotous Poſture, the Juſtices and Sheriffs, with the power of the County, might reſort to the place, and view the force, and record it; but this was too dangerous an imployment for them, when an Army of Horſe and Foot could not undertake it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hazard: and if few or no other Witneſſes are left, it were to impoſe too much irrationality on our Law, that by the Rules of it Treaſon might paſs with impunity: to prevent which, the Law hath recourſe, in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary caſes, to extraordinary means: It is a Maxim, <hi>Quod remedio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituitur ipſa re valet ſi culpa abſit:</hi> and therefore the Law will allow an <hi>Avowry</hi> without <hi>Atturmnent,</hi> where he hath no means to compel the Teſt to atturn, 6 <hi>Co.</hi> 68. <hi>a.</hi> ſo where Impediments happen by the Act of God, the Law judges according to the neceſſity. If one be bound to repair a Bank of the Sea, if he (by negligence) ſuffer the Waters to ſurround his Neighbours ground, he is lyable to waſt; but if by violence of Tempeſt, an Innundation happen, he is excuſable. If the Heir at full age tender Livery, and dyeth before he hath made homage, the Law gives him the advantage of his Tender in the ſame way, as if it had been accompanyed with all the ſolemn Circumſtancies attending it: If a Diſſeiſor die ſeized, the Diſſeiſee being in Priſon, or beyond the Seas, it is no diſcent, <hi>Finch</hi> Nom. 17. <hi>Neceſsitas vincit communem legem:</hi> and therefore, if two Joynt-Tenants be of Land, and to the Heirs of one of them, they ſhall not joyn in a Writ of Right and yet they ſhall joyn in a Writ of Right of an Advowſon: For if they ſhall not joyn, neither the one nor the other hath any remedy, 5 <hi>Cr.</hi> 40. b. <hi>Illud quod alias licitum non est neceſsit as facit licitum &amp; neceſsit as inducit privilegium quod jure privatur:</hi> And upon this ground was the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93645:21"/>Biſhop of <hi>Salisburies</hi> Caſe judged of the grant of an Office, with an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity contrary to the Statute, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, was there ever greater neceſſity, is not the ſettlement of the Kingdom in its critical hower, is not the Banes publiſht, Now to give evidence, or for ever after hold our peace? Do not nocent perſons paſs in triumphant innocency, whileſt thoſe ſtand by, whoſe evidence, if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, would write the Letter of Condemnation on their fore-heads? Theſe were the men that broke through the Hoaſt to draw water, to get e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, by marching into the enemies quarters daily encountring them, and now the water muſt be ſpilt on the ground, and they denied to ſay, they ever did ſee them: This is worſe then to muzzel the mouth of the Oxe, whileſt he treads out the ſtraw; Perſons in many caſes may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, where the conſequence may be to obviate a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nalty, they may be ſubjected unto; A Sheriff may be examined upon his own return. A for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Plea may be ſworn; An Infant levies a Fine, and brings a Writ of Error to reverſe it, yet he may be examined; Debt upon arrerages of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, the Plaintiff may be ſworn if there be any ſuch accompt, and by this he takes away the benefit of the Defendant to wage the Law: The party rob'd upon the Statute of <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> ſhall be examined, and ſo upon a forcible entry, though the party may have reſtitution, yet he may be examined; In a Writ of Entry brought, an Eſſoin was caſt for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant in the Kings Service, <hi>in partibus tranſmarinus,</hi> and the Eſſoiner was examined and ſworn <hi>de veritate eſſoinæ,</hi> Dyer 154.</p>
            <p>I might proceed, that <hi>licet iniquum eſt aliquem ſuæ rei eſse judicem,</hi> yet in ſome caſes one may be judge, Maſter and Carver: <hi>Leſſor</hi> Covenants to repair the Houſe, if he do not, and the Leſſee doth it, he may pay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the Rent, 12 <hi>H.</hi> 8.11. Taylors and Hoſtlers may detain the Garment and Horſe, till reaſonable ſatisfaction be made.</p>
            <p>It may be added, how little thoſe Officers ſerving his Majeſty before 49. are ſubjected to thoſe temptations, upon which the Law in its rigour grounds it ſelf, to exclude intereſted perſons from being Witneſſes; The bulk of that remote poſſibility of ſatisfaction, is but gleanings and frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (their reward is, that they know his Majeſty hath an eſteem of their ſervices and ſufferings,) joyn that with the worth of the perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Commiſſioned Officers, and then who could without injury to the Law of charity judge them, that to preſerve thoſe Oaths of Allegiance &amp; Supremacy they have ſworn, inviol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly have put no rate upon their lives and fortunes, and have not worſhipt the Idols of the times, though the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93645:21"/>Oven was ſeven times heated, I ſay, Who can judge, nay think, that for an acre of Land to be divided among them, they would ſtoop to ſo ſordid a crime as Perjury: The Peers of the Realm, upon this account, paſs upon tryals of blood, only declaring their Judgments upon their Honour: But ſurely cur caſe is plain, and that they are not only lawful Witneſſes, but under ſtrong Obligations, if any perſon be indicted of Treaſon, to give in evidence, their knowledg in matter of fact, Tenant for life, and the Remainder over: If Tenant for life be indicted for Treaſon, he in the Remainder may be a witneſs, though in that caſe, when one goes to the bough, the other goes to the plough.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 20. <hi>Upon motion to the Court, that any aged or impotent Perſon that can give evidence for his Majeſty, That their depoſitions be taken by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and lodged in the Court, to be produc't in his Majesties behalf, at the ſame ſhall require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not denyed in the caſe of the Subject; Commiſſioners to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>in perpetuam rei memoriam,</hi> are frequent; It is but reaſon to uſe all good Husbandry for the King, and to pickle up ſuch proofs, as through age cannot keep long.</p>
            <p>Thus may it pleaſe your Grace, I have paſt by thoſe ſeveral heads given me in charge by the Houſe, humbly to preſent to your Grace, with the inſtance of ſome of thoſe many reaſons they had under their conſideration; The concluſion of the Inſtrument is this, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe are the particulars which are preſented to his Grace and Council, as the reſult of the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations which have been hitherto made upon the late proceedings; And that this Houſe humbly deſires his Grace, that when time and experience ſhall ſuggeſt any thing of like moment with the above particulars, his Grace and Council will be pleaſed to receive them: And if any thing herein offered, through the ſtrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs of time, be not ſufficiently cleared, his Grace and Council would be pleaſed to admit a Committee of the Houſe of Commons, to confer with a Committee of the Board upon the ſame; and that, in the interim, if any cauſe to be heard by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, may receive prejudice under any of theſe Propoſals, being unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that the Commiſſioners being aſcertained of the ſame, may ſuſpend the hearing of it, till his Grace and Councils pleaſure be further known.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93645:22"/>
            <p>It reſts only to beg your Graces pardon, if in diſcharging the truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in me, I have been enforced to uſe ſome words of Diſcrimination, It is againſt the Inclination, nay, the Prayers of the Houſe (if the Subject matter could diſpence with it) to avoid them: They know, the compleat peace of the Kingdom, reſts not in ceſſation of Arms, but in union of Hearts; and they doubt not, but under the prudent Adminiſtration of his Majeſties Authority veſted in your Grace, we ſhall arrive to that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that it may be ſaid, <hi>Jam cuncti gens una ſumus;</hi> ah Sir, and <hi>Sic ſimus in ævum:</hi> We complain not of the want of a good Law, for the ſettlement of this Nation upon ſure and laſting foundations, ſuch that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our ſins can ſubvert: If the ſpirits of all Kings living had been textacted, they could not have contributed more to revive a gaſping Kingdom, than the wiſdom of our Royal Soveraign, bleſt with a Divine aſſiſtance, hath in this Act of Settlement recorded, to perfume and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm his memory to all ages: But Sir, <hi>Corruptio optimi est peſſima:</hi> It is not the Sword, but the hand that gives Protection, or a Wound, with reſpect to the efficient cauſe: The Law ſaith, All-hail-Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but if the execution be diſſonant, we are crucified under a glorious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Mockery.</p>
            <p>The execution of the Law, is the ſoul of the Law; the want of this hath tranſmitted this never-dying Truth to Poſterity, That <hi>Nulla eſt ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſera ſervitus, quam ubi jus eſt incertum &amp; vagum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:93645:22"/>
            <p>February 13. 1662.</p>
            <p>ORdered by the Houſe <hi>nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente,</hi> That M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Speaker ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this day ſo faithfully deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſenſe of this Houſe, unto his Grace the Lord Lieutenant: Do cauſe his Speech to be Printed and Publiſhed, and that it be entred into the Journal of this Houſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Philip Fernely,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="copyright_notice">
            <p>I <hi>Do appoint Alderman</hi> William Bladen <hi>to Print my Speech: And that none elſe preſume to Print it without my Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>AUDLEY MERVYN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
